<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://helmer.aksis.uib.no/menota/guidelines/tools/dtd/norron.dtd"
[
<!ATTLIST figure url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ATTLIST xptr url CDATA #IMPLIED>]
>
<TEI.2 lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Description of UB Bergen MS 1549, 1, a-d</title>
                <author>Åslaug Ommundsen</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Bergen University Library</publisher>
                <address><addrLine>Nygå̴rdsgaten 5, NO-5005 Bergen</addrLine><addrLine>http://www.ub.uib.no</addrLine></address>
                <date>2005</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDescription>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Bergen University Library, Art and Humanities Library</settlement>
                        <repository>Bergen University Library</repository>
                        <idno>MS 1549, 1, a-d</idno>
                        <altName type="old signature">MS 410, 1</altName>
                        <altName>Br 4 (Gjerløw)</altName>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msHeading>
                        <title>The Botulph Breviary fragments</title>
                        <note type="schlagzeile">Parchment, four fragments: a: ca 17x18 cm, b: ca
                            25x14 cm, c and d: ca 12x3 cm, (original size: ca 25x18 cm), <placeName>England</placeName>,
                            <date>late 13th century</date>.</note>
                    </msHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <p>a: St Botulph's day, 17 June: The fragment contains parts of paragraphs
                            five to nine of the nocturnal readings of Matins on St Botulph's day, 17
                            June. The readings correspond with St Botulph's Vita in Acta sanctorum,
                            Junius IV, p. 402, which was issued by Folcard, abbot of Thorney, in
                            1070. The divisions, however, do not correspond entirely with the Vita,
                            because of steps taken to fit eleven chapters into nine readings. Our
                            text begins with the last few lines of lesson five, with the king
                            granting Botulph land for his monastery. Lesson six is the only complete
                            lesson, not missing any parts due to the sorry state of the fragment. In
                            the sixth lesson Botulph finds Ikanho (here spelled "kanho"), and
                            decides to settle there, even though the deserted place is full of
                            demons. In the seventh lesson, which for some reason is missing its
                            rubric, Botulph exorcises the demons in spite of their pleas. Lesson
                            eight begins with the flight of the demons, and goes on with the
                            building of the monastery of Ikanho, "equal to those of France", and
                            Botulph's gathering and teaching of the brothers. The ninth lesson
                            describes Botulph's virtues, his last years among his followers, and,
                            finally, his death, when God calls him from the prison of the flesh to
                            his coronation in heaven, to the tears and lament of his fellow
                            brothers. The shorter vita of the Schleswig breviary is entirely
                            different from the one presented here. The Schleswig text clearly states
                            that Botulph was Scottish, and from this we can probably interpret the
                            sentence in lesson nine, that he was loved by everyone, "also the
                            neighbouring inhabitants of his fatherland."</p>
                        <p> b: the Annunciation, 25 March: On fragment b we have the end of the
                            first Vesper and the beginning of the Matins for the Annunciation, 25
                            March. The fragment begins with the second verse of the hymn Ave maris
                            stella (CAO 8272). Next follows instruction for the verse Rorate celi,
                            followed by the antiphon for the Magnificat, the Ingressus angelus (CAO
                            3339), complete with musical notation. The prayer Deus, qui de beate
                            marie virginis utero, ends the vesper. Then comes the invitatory of the
                            Matins (curiously enough spelled "Inuitiatorum"), Ave maria gratia plena
                            (CAO 1539), with instructions for the psalm Venite. The hymn Quem terra
                            pontus is indicated, and then comes the rubric for the first Nocturn.
                            The antiphons and psalms follow in this order: Ant. Prophete
                            predicaverunt (CAO 4392). Ps. Domine dominus. Ant. Rorate celi (CAO
                            4668). Ps. Celi enarrant. Ant. Egredietur virga (CAO 2613). Ps. Domini.
                            V. Exyon (sic). Then comes the first lesson, followed by the responsory
                            Ingressus angelus (CAO 6963). The second lesson is followed by the
                            responsory [Suscipe] verbum (CAO 7744). The fragment ends with the third
                            lesson.</p>
                        <p> c. and d. St. Philip and St. Jacob, 1. May: The fragment c and d are
                            taken from the same page, with c as the upper part and d as the lower.
                            Fragment c beginning with "non bibit" contains a reading on St Jacob,
                            referring to his chaste way of life: He never drank wine, ate animal
                            flesh, cut his hair or bathed. Fragment d then goes on with an
                            unidentified reading. The verso-side of c continues with a reading on St
                            Philip, describing how he preached to the Scythians for twenty years and
                            was later buried there, and how his virgin daughters were buried with
                            him. This was the final reading, since it is followed by Te Deum, which
                            finishes Matins. The verso-side of fragment d continues with an antiphon
                            for Lauds of the same Saint's feast, followed by the psalm Dominus
                            regnavit and the antiphon Ego sum via (CAO 2603)</p>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>Parchment, four fragments, <dimensions>2a: ca 17x18 cm, b: ca 25x14 cm, c
                                and d: ca 12x3 cm, (original size: ca 25x18 cm)</dimensions></p>
                        <p>Lay-out: Ruled with a lead point. The top line frames the writing space,
                            which has been ca 21 x 14,5 cm. Two columns, 6,5 cm wide. Originally 36
                            lines to each column.</p>
                        <p>Script: Gothic textualis, written with a pen with a thick nib. Short
                            ascenders and descenders. This seems to be a product of a transitional
                            phase, since two types of a occur; most a's are closed, but some are
                            still open and with a rounder shape. The insular abbreviation-sign for
                            est ÷ occurs (b verso, third line). Rubricated.</p>
                        <p>Musical notation: Square notation on four red lines. Clefs: c, f and b.</p>
                        <p>Initials: Fleuronné in blue, red and possibly green. The initials appear
                            in a hierarchy, from the minor, plain alternating red and blue initials
                            over one line in the verses of the hymn Ave maris stella to the large
                            and flourished initial P (over six lines) of Prophete predicaverunt, the
                            first antiphon of the first nocturne. The first letters of the prayers
                            and readings are flourished or plain alternating red and blue initials
                            over two lines.</p>
                        <p>Condition: Fragment a is not in a very good condition. Particularly the
                            verso side is quite worn and darkened, and parts of the text is
                            difficult to read. Fragment b is the largest and best preserved fragment
                            in this group, although it has a 2,5 cm fold on the left margin of the
                            verso side, hiding the left part of the text in the column. For the top
                            6 cm it is possible to peek underneath the fold, but later the fold
                            sticks to the parchment underneath. The fragments a, b and c have holes
                            in them from the binding.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <p><placeName>England</placeName>, possibly <placeName>Eastern England</placeName>, in the <date>late 13th century</date>. The nine
                                lesson celebration of St. Botulph's day, the characteristic feature
                                of this Breviary, is taken from the English Vita. In <placeName>Scandinavia</placeName> the
                                Schleswig Breviary (1512) and Uppsala (1496) also have nine
                                readings, but these are taken from another Vita, possibly of
                                Scandinavian origin. Nidaros (1519) has six readings, while the
                                English sees York and Hereford only have three, and the use of Sarum
                                does not celebrate Botulph at all. The breviary may have originated
                                in Eastern England, because of the strong Botulph's cult in that
                                area.</p>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance>
                            <p>Secondary provenance unknown.</p>
                        </provenance>
                        <acquisition>
                            <p>MS 1549,1a-e was a gift to the <orgName>museum of Bergen</orgName> from <persName>cand. theol. H.
                                Daae</persName> in <date>1829</date>. The H. Daae in question is probably <persName>Hans Daae
                                (<dateRange>1808-65</dateRange>)</persName>, born in <placeName>Leikanger</placeName> as son of the minister there. He began
                                his theology studies in <placeName>Christiania</placeName> in <date>1825</date>. In <date>1831</date> he was employed
                                as a chaplain in <placeName>Korskirken (the Cross Church) in Bergen</placeName>, where he
                                stayed until <date>1850</date>. The circumstances for the gift, or where Daae
                                acquired the fragments, is not known.</p>
                        </acquisition>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <listBibl>
                            <head>Bibliography</head>
                            <bibl>Acta sanctorum, Junius III, Paris &amp; Rome 1867, p. 402-403
                                (for St Botulph).</bibl>
                            <bibl>Acta sanctorum, Maii I, 1-5, Paris &amp; Rome 1867, p. 12A and
                                p. 21F (for Sts Philip &amp; Jacob).</bibl>
                            <bibl>Gjerløw, Lilli (ed.) 1968: Ordo Nidrosiensis ecclesiae, Oslo, n.
                                p. 351.</bibl>
                            <bibl>Toy, John 2003: "St. Botulph: An English saint in Scandinavia",
                                The Cross goes North, York, pp. 565-570.</bibl>
                            <bibl>Tveitane, Mattias et. al.: Bergen University Library Manuscript
                                Catalogue [unpublished]</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                </msDescription>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2006.02.16</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Tone Merete Bruvik</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added encoding of dates, persons etc.</item>
            </change><change>
                <date>2005.08.17</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Tone Merete Bruvik</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Recoded the content of the history element.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2004.11.01</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Tone Merete Bruvik</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Updated with references to facsimiles, added revisionDesc, language
                    declaration etc.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2004.10.?</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Åslaug Ommundsen</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Made the original</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The so-called Botulph Breviary fragments is a group of four fragments from the
                    same Breviary, written in England in the late thirteenth century. One of the
                    fragments contains the readings six to nine for the Matins of St Botulph's day
                    (17 June, in Scotland 25 June). Nine readings constitute the highest degree of a
                    saint's feast. St Botulph was a popular saint in Eastern England and Scotland,
                    and the Botulph breviary was therefore perhaps written in Eastern England. The
                    lessons six to nine, more or less extant in our fragment a, describe Botulph's
                    discovery of Ikanho (possibly the present Iken in Suffolk, east of Ipswich), the
                    exorcism of the area's demons, the building of the monastery (in 654), and,
                    finally, to the great lament of his fellow brothers, Botulph's death (in 680).
                    Apart from the readings of St Botulph's day, the fragments contain parts of the
                    liturgy of the feast days of the Annunciation (25 March) and of the Saints
                    Philip and Jacob (1 May).</p>
                <list type="facsimiles">
                    <head>Facsimiles and transcriptions</head>
                    <item>
                        <xref url="../transcriptions/UBB MS 1549, 1a-transkr.page">Transcription of
                            UBB MS 1549, 1a.</xref>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1a 1.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1a, recto</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1a 2.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1a, verso.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref url="../transcriptions/UBB MS 1549, 1b-transkr.page">Transcription of
                            UBB MS 1549, 1b.</xref>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1b 1.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1b, recto</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1b 2.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1b, verso.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref url="../transcriptions/UBB MS 1549, 1c-transkr.page">Transcription of
                            UBB MS 1549, 1c.</xref>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1c 2.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1c, recto</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1c 1.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1c, verso.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <xref url="../transcriptions/UBB MS 1549, 1d-transkr.page">Transcription of
                            UBB MS 1549, 1d.</xref>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1d 1.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1d, recto</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure url="../facsimiles/UBB MS 1549, 1d 2.jpg">
                            <figDesc>UBB MS 1549 1d, verso.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
